An Inventory of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection Records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Central office records (Box 25)
  - Public relations and conference promotion
    - White House conference--Current information, 1930 February - April. (Folder 30: 3)
    - White House happenings, 1931 September - 1932 December. (Folder 30: 4)
  - Conference on Care and Protection of Children, 1930 January 4 - 1933 February 6. (Folder 30: 5)
    Cover sheets from Ray Lyman Wilbur's personal files
  - Children's Bureau, 1929-1930. (Folder 30: 6)
    Charts, correspondence, list of needs and services, memoranda, printed matter, and miscellany
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur--Speeches, 1928-1932. (Box-folder 31: 1)
    Includes notes and printed matter
  - Acknowledgments concerning closing of the conference, 1932. (Folder 31: 2)
    Mostly Ray Lyman Wilbur's correspondence
  - Correspondence concerning originals requested, 1929-1931 (Folder 31: 3)
  - American Relief Administration (A. R. A.) Children's Fund, Inc.--Correspondence, including Edgar Rickard, Raymond H. Sawtelle, and others, 1929-1933. (Folder 31: 4-5)
    Includes financial records, memoranda, and telegram
  - Financial records. (Box 32)
    - Voucher statements, 1929-1932 (Folder 32: 1-4)
    - Budgets, 1929-1930 and undated (Folder 32: 5-9)
    - Payroll data, 1930-1932 (Folder 32: 10-11)
    - Internal Revenue Service, 1930-1931. (Folder 32: 12)
      Annual returns
    - Statement of expenditures, 1930-1931 (Folder 32: 13-14)
  - Inter-office correspondence regarding personnel, 1929-1938 (Folder 32: 15)
  - Payroll records, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 33: 1)
  - Excerpts from reports of committees of Section I, 1931 and undated. (Folder 33: 2)
    Includes addresses
  - Correspondence--Samuel McC. Hamill and others, 1931-1939. (Folder 33: 3)
    Includes list of members of Continuation Committee, publications of Section I (Medical Service), and notes
- Committee on Medical Service (Box 34)
  - Mildred Morse, 1929-1932. (Folder 34: 1)
    Correspondence and telegram
  - Samuel McC. Hamill, chairman, 1929-1930. (Folder 34: 2)
  - Expense records, 1930-1932 (Folder 34: 3)
  - Payroll data, 1929-1931 (Folder 34: 4)
- Committee on Growth and Development, Section IA
  - Statements of expenditures, 1930-1931 (Folder 34: 5)
  - Kenneth D. Blackfan, chairman, 1929-1950 and undated. (Folder 34: 6-7)
    Biographical information about Bronson Crothers, agenda and minutes of meeting, correspondence, list of chairmen of subcommittees, memoranda, statement of objectives, survey report, and telegram
  - Committee A, 1930. (Box-folder 35: 1)
    Proceedings and schedule
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932. (Folder 35: 2)
    Includes financial records, note, statement, and telegrams
  - Expense records, 1929-1932. (Folder 35: 3)
  - Letters of acceptances of membership and willingness to cooperate with Kenneth D. Blackfan, chairman of the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 35: 4)
  - Central office records, 1929-1931. (Folder 35: 5-6)
    Includes agenda of meetings, correspondence, and lists of committee personnel and chairmen of various sections
- Committee on Prenatal and Maternal Care, Section IB
  - Miscellany, 1929-1934. (Folder 35: 7)
    Includes book reviews, chairman's (Fred L. Adair) address, correspondence, memoranda, notes, and telegrams
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 36: 1-2)
    Address; article; lists of chairmen of subcommittees of Committee IB; list of deaths from causes associated with pregnancy and childbirth in the United States; memoranda; minutes of meetings; outline of activities and composition of committee, Section IID; press release; and report
  - Expense records, 1929-1932. (Folder 36: 3)
  - Letters of acceptance to serve on the committee and willingness to assist, 1929-1930 (Folder 36: 4)
  - Central office records, 1929-1931. (Folder 36: 5-6)
    Correspondence, list of members and sectional chairmen, notes, and telegram
  - Central office records--Washington, 1929-1933. (Box-folder 37: 1)
    Includes article, correspondence, report, statement, and telegram regarding publication, and miscellany
  - Hugh Cumming, 1929-1931. (Folder 37: 2)
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1929-1932. (Folder 37: 3)
- General correspondence, 1929-1932. (Folder 37: 4-6)
  Includes article, report, study, telegram, and related materials
- Committee on Medical Care for Children, Section IC
  - Philip Van Ingen, chairman, 1929-1932. (Folder 37: 7)
    Correspondence, financial records, and telegram
  - Report of the proceedings of the meeting of the Section on Medical Service, New York City, 1930 (Folder 37: 8)
  - Philip Van Ingen (Box 38)
    - Correspondence, summary of lectures by Sherman L. Davis, and telegrams, 1929-1932 (Folder 38: 1)
    - Progress reports, 1930-1931. (Folder 38: 2)
      Includes family interview survey, minutes of meeting, program, and miscellany
    - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932 (Folder 38: 3)
    - Results of family interview survey and survey of the use of preventive medical service for preschool children presented at a meeting, Washington, D.C., 1931 (Folder 38: 4)
    - Expense records, 1930-1931. (Folder 38: 5)
    - Acceptance letters from individuals invited to serve on the committee, 1929/1931 (Folder 38: 6)
    - Addresses by individuals on various committees and subcommittees, 1931. (Folder 38: 7)
      Includes abstract of speech by Philip Van Ingen, chairman of the committee
    - Central office records, 1931. (Folder 38: 8-9)
      Miscellany
- Committee on Public Health Service and Administration, Section II, Hugh S. Cumming, chairman, 1929-1932. (Box-folder 39: 1)
  Biographical information about George H. Bigelow and H. A. Whittaker, correspondence, lists of committee members, and report
- Committee on Public Health Organization, Section IIA
  - E. L. Bishop, chairman, 1929-1933. (Folder 39: 2-4)
    Announcement, correspondence, financial record, list of recommendations, memoranda, minutes of meeting, printed matter, program, report, and telegram
  - Expense records, 1929-1930. (Folder 39: 5)
  - Payroll data, 1930-1931. (Folder 39: 6)
  - Statements of expenditures by sections, 1930-1931 (Folder 39: 7)
  - Report of the conference sessions, Committee C, Medical Care for Children, Washington, D.C., 1931 (Folder 39: 8)
  - Special legislative records, 1929-1930. (Box-folder 40: 1)
    Includes agenda and minutes of meeting, comments by chairman of special committees, correspondence, medical bulletin, printed matter, statement of general principles relating to public health, plan for federal assistance, telegram, and miscellany
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931. (Folder 40: 2)
    Includes bulletin, clipping, and report
  - Letters of acceptance to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 40: 3)
  - Official records, 1930-1931. (Folder 40: 4)
    Includes correspondence and lists of committee personnel
  - Abstract of reports, 1930 and undated. (Folder 40: 5)
  - Expense records, 1929-1931. (Folder 40: 6)
- Committee on Communicable Disease Control, Section IIB
  - George H. Bigelow, chairman, 1929-1930. (Folder 40: 7)
    Abstract of report, correspondence, list of committee personnel, and telegram
  - Report, 1930 (Folder 40: 8)
  - General, 1930-1931 and undated. (Box-folder 41: 1)
    Correspondence, lists of committee members, statistical data, summary of the report, and related materials
  - Expense records, 1929-1930. (Folder 41: 2)
  - Acceptance letters for membership, 1929 (Folder 41: 3)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1931. (Folder 41: 4)
- Committee on Milk Production and Control, Section IIC
  - General, 1930-1932. (Folder 41: 5)
    Correspondence, report, and telegrams
  - Editorial correspondence, 1928-1932. (Folder 41: 6)
    Includes preliminary report, statistical data, and 2 photographic prints depicting World's Dairy Banquet, National Dairy Exposition, Memphis, Tennessee, 1928, and Quality Creamery Company, National Dairy Exposition, St. Louis, Missouri, 1928
  - H. A. Whittaker, chairman, 1929-1930. (Folder 41: 7)
  - Expense records, 1929-1931. (Folder 41: 8)
  - Acceptance letters for membership, 1929-1930. (Folder 41: 9)
  - Central office records, 1930-1931. (Folder 41: 10)
    Includes correspondence, list of committee members, and related materials
- Committee on Education and Training, Section III (Box 42)
  - Frederick James Kelly, chairman, 1929-1930. (Folder 42: 1)
    Address, biographical information, correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meeting, printed matter, program, statement of purpose, summary report, and telegram. Includes 1 photographic print depicting Kelly, undated
  - Financial records, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 42: 2-3)
    Statements of expenditure
  - Payroll data, 1929-1930. (Folder 42: 4)
  - Committee on Family and Parent Education, Section IIIA
    - Louise Stanley, chairman, 1929-1935 and undated. (Folder 42: 5)
      Biographical information, correspondence, clipping, list of committee members, minutes of meeting, outline, printed matter, report, study, and miscellany
    - Martha Van Rensselaer, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 42: 6)
      Correspondence, outline of article, remarks, report, and telegram
- Proceedings of the informal dinner discussion in connection with the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, American Women's Association, New York City, 1931 (Folder 42: 7)
- Committee on Family and Parent Education, Section IIIA (Box 43)
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932 and undated. (Folder 43: 1)
    Includes bibliography and note
  - Louise Stanley, 1929-1930. (Folder 43: 2)
    Letters of acceptance
  - Central office records, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 43: 3)
    Correspondence, list of members and section chairmen, and outline
  - Expense records, 1929-1932. (Folder 43: 4)
  - Martha Van Rensselaer, chairman, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 43: 5)
    Correspondence, memoranda, instructions for selection of families for interview and for interviewer, report, and telegram
- Committee on Infant and Preschool Child, Section IIIB
  - John E. Anderson, chairman, 1929-1935. (Folder 43: 6-7)
    Comments and suggestions from committee members, correspondence, printed matter, report, telegram, and miscellany
  - Mrs. J. E. King, 1929-1930. (Folder 43: 8)
    Clipping, correspondence, and telegram
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932 and undated. (Box-folder 44: 1)
    Includes abstract and outline of report, telegram, and related materials
  - Expense records, 1929-1931. (Folder 44: 2)
  - Acceptance letters to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 44: 3)
  - Central office records, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 44: 4)
    Includes correspondence and lists of personnel
- Committee on the School Child, Section IIIC
  - Reports of the subcommittees on
    - Health education in secondary schools, 1930 (Folder 44: 5)
    - Health education in the elementary schools, 1930 (Folder 44: 6)
    - Health problems in the kindergarten, 1930 (Folder 44: 7)
    - Preliminary reports of the subcommittees, 1930 (Folder 44: 8)
  - Program for professional training of teachers and leaders, 1932 and undated (Folder 44: 9)
  - Thomas D. Wood--Correspondence, 1931-1938. (Folder 44: 10)
    Includes minutes of meeting, note, and progress report
  - Thomas D. Wood--Correspondence, 1929-1930. (Box-folder 45: 1-3)
    Includes biographical information, lists of entrance requirements and committee members, minutes of meeting, notes, printed matter, program, questionnaire, report, schedule, study, and telegram. Includes 1 photographic print depicting Wood, undated
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932. (Folder 45: 4)
    Includes list of members, memoranda, and telegram
  - Expense records, 1930-1931. (Folder 45: 5)
  - Letters of acceptance to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 45: 6)
  - Central office records, 1929-1931. (Folder 45: 7)
    Includes correspondence, financial records, list of members and section chairmen, and miscellany
- Committee on Vocational Guidance and Child Labor, Section IIID (Box 46)
  - Anne S. Davis, chairman--Correspondence, 1929-1933. (Folder 46: 1)
    Includes address by Ray Lyman Wilbur, biographical information of Anne Davis, list of committee personnel, minutes of meeting, note, telegram, and related materials. Also includes 1 photographic print depicting Davis, undated
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932. (Folder 46: 2)
    Includes article, memoranda, note, and pamphlet
  - Expense records, 1929-1931. (Folder 46: 3)
  - Acceptance letters from individuals invited to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 46: 4)
  - Central office records, 1929-1930 and undated. (Folder 46: 5)
    Correspondence and lists of committee personnel
- Committee on Recreation and Physical Education, Section IIIE
  - Henry Breckinridge, chairman, 1929-1932. (Folder 46: 6-7)
    Excerpts from address by Ray Lyman Wilbur, correspondence, list of heads of men's organizations, memorandum, minutes of meeting, notes, printed matter, and study
  - Expense records, 1929-1930. (Folder 46: 8)
  - Editorial correspondence, 1930-1932. (Folder 46: 9)
    Includes memoranda, note, and reports
  - Letters of acceptance from individuals willing to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Box-folder 47: 1)
  - Central office records, 1930-1931. (Folder 47: 2)
    Includes correspondence, list of committee personnel, memoranda, and note
- Committee on Special Education of the Handicapped and Gifted, Section IIIF
  - Charles S. Berry, chairman, 1929-1932. (Folder 47: 3-4)
    Biographical information, correspondence, list of committee personnel, notes, program, telegram, and related materials
  - Expense records, 1930-1932. (Folder 47: 5)
  - Central office records, 1929-1931 and undated. (Folder 47: 6)
    Includes correspondence, lists of committee personnel, note, and telegram
  - Letters of acceptance from individuals willing to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 47: 7)
  - 45 photographic prints, including some unidentified ones, depicting training facilities for mentally and physically challenged children in Ohio and Minnesota; toys, curtains, draperies, furniture, lamp, and rug made by handicapped children and being used to decorate bedroom, sunroom, and sitting area; and children receiving reading lessons, undated (Folder 47: 8)
- Committee on Youth Outside of Home and School, Section IIIG
  - Cinema in education, 1933-1934 and undated. (Folder 47: 9)
    Correspondence, introductory note by James E. West, printed matter, and report
  - Correspondence relating to editorial problems, 1931-1933. (Box-folder 48: 1)
    Includes article and report
  - James E. West, chairman, 1929-1934. (Folder 48: 2-3)
    Articles, biographical information, clipping, copy of the Children's Charter, financial records, lists of chairmen of various sections and members of Section IIIG, memorandum, notes, printed matter, report, statement, telegrams, and miscellany. Also includes 2 photographic prints depicting West, undated
  - Expense records, 1930-1932. (Folder 48: 4)
    Correspondence and statements of receipts and expenses
  - Letters of acceptance from individuals invited to join the committee, 1930 (Folder 48: 5)
  - Central office records, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 48: 6)
    Includes correspondence, lists of committee personnel, outline, printed matter, and miscellany
- Committee on the Handicapped, Section IV (Box 49)
  - C. C. Carstens, chairman, 1929-1939. (Folder 49: 1-2)
    Correspondence, draft report, financial records, minutes of meetings, organizational chart, printed matter, proceedings of the general sessions, and telegram
  - Expense records, 1929-1931. (Folder 49: 3)
  - Payroll data, 1929-1931. (Folder 49: 4)
  - Statements of expenditures by sections, 1930-1931 (Folder 49: 5)
  - Report, 1930-1931. (Folder 49: 6)
    Joint study for Sections IVA and IVC
  - Joint county study for all committees in Section IV, 1929-1930. (Box-folder 50: 1)
    Includes correspondence, list of local public administration units, minutes of meetings of research secretaries and chairman of Local Unit Committees, and reports of the field studies
  - Statistics Committee, 1930. (Folder 50: 2)
    Includes correspondence, memorandum, report, and related materials
- Committee on National, State and Local Organizations for the Handicapped, Section IVA
  - Kate B. Johnson, chairman, 1929-1932. (Folder 50: 3-4)
    Correspondence, list of committee personnel, memorandum, note, outline, questionnaire, report, schedule of meetings, telegram, and related materials
  - Minutes of committee meetings, 1930. (Folder 50: 5)
    Includes outline of Committee on Private Agencies and its relationships to public agencies, reports, and statement relating to the work of Section IVA
  - Expense record, 1929-1932. (Folder 50: 6)
    Includes correspondence and telegram
  - Letters of acceptance from individuals invited to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 50: 7)
  - Central office records, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 50: 8)
    Includes correspondence, list of committee personnel, note, and related materials
  - Chairman's office files (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, 1929-1930 and undated. (Folder 51: 1-2)
      Includes list of members and subcommittees, outline of program for state and local public and private organizations, press release, president's speech, and related materials
    - Correspondence between Kate B. Johnson and Mary S. Labaree, 1930. (Folder 51: 3)
      Includes notes and statement concerning work of Section IVA
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and related materials, 1929-1930 (Folder 51: 4-5)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee, 1929-1930. (Folder 51: 6-7)
      Includes agenda, correspondence, list of members, memoranda, outline, schedule, and telegram, 1929-1930
  - Direct Care, Subcommittee of State Department Committee
    - Correspondence, 1930 and undated. (Folder 51: 8)
      Includes articles relating to various systems of child care in different states, outline, maps of direct care, minutes of meeting, study, and related materials
    - Reports, 1930. (Folder 51: 9)
      Includes correspondence, comments on draft report, memoranda, outline, and related materials
  - Committee on the Handicapped, Section IV, 1930. (Folder 51: 10)
    Proceedings of sessions
- Committee on National, State and Local Organizations for the Handicapped, Section IVA (Box 52)
  - Sophonisba P. Breckinridge, 1930-1931 and undated. (Folder 52: 1)
    Article, comments on state and private agencies, correspondence, memorandum, organization of state departments, report, telegram, and related materials
  - James H. Foster, Subcommittee of State Department Committee, 1930 and undated. (Folder 52: 2)
    Correspondence, excerpts of article, comments on the subcommittee report, memorandum, and minutes of meeting
- Committee on Physically and Mentally Handicapped, Section IVB
  - William J. Ellis, chairman, 1930-1933 and undated (Folder 52: 3-4)
    Agenda, comments of William A. White, correspondence, list of committee members, minutes of meeting, statement, summary report, and telegram. Also includes 1 photographic print depicting Ellis, undated
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1933. (Folder 52: 5)
  - Proceedings of organization meeting, New York City, 1929 (Folder 52: 6)
- Committee on National, State and Local Organizations for the Handicapped, Section IVA (Box 53)
  - Subcommittee on Form and Equipment, Agnes H. Hanna, 1930 and undated. (Folder 53: 1)
    Correspondence, list of topics to be considered by the subcommittee, minutes of meeting, preliminary statement on the summary and recommendations, and report
  - Subcommittee on Finance, 1930 and undated. (Folder 53: 2-3)
    Includes budget for Division A, correspondence, expense records, financial statements, note, reimbursement voucher, and related materials
  - Subcommittee on Interstate Relations, 1930 and undated. (Folder 53: 4-5)
    Article on dealing with the problem of runaway children, agreement between states, correspondence, map, minutes of meeting, outline and report on the problem of maintaining interstate relationship in a federal system, scope of work for the committee, and study on child labor
  - Subcommittee on Local Units, 1929-1930 and undated. (Folder 53: 6-7)
    List of names of superintendents by county, minutes of meetings, notes, outline for materials needed, printed matter, reports, schedule of meetings, study by state of different aspects of child care, and telegram
  - Subcommittee on Private Agencies and Relationship to the Public, 1930 and undated. (Folder 53: 8-9)
    Correspondence, memoranda, outline for description of per capita payments by local government units, report, and statement
- Committee on Physically and Mentally Handicapped, Section IVB (Box 54)
  - Expense records, 1930-1932. (Folder 54: 1)
  - Letters of acceptance, 1929-1930. (Folder 54: 2)
    Correspondence and list of committee members
  - Central office records, 1930-1931. (Folder 54: 3)
    Correspondence; list of chairmen and members of sections, subsections, and committees; and outline of studies
- Committee on Socially Handicapped Dependency and Neglect, Section IVC-1
  - Minutes of special meeting, 1930 (Folder 54: 4)
  - Central office records
  - General, 1930-1932. (Folder 54: 5-6)
    Biographical sketch of Homer Folks, chairman; correspondence; note; printed matter; report; telegram; and 1 photographic print depicting Folks, undated
  - Minutes of meeting, 1929-1930. (Folder 54: 7)
    Includes correspondence and outline of report
  - Form letters to committee, 1929-1930 (Box-folder 55: 1)
  - Letters relating to the outline of subject matter for the committee to consider, 1929 (Folder 55: 2)
  - Remarks on report, 1930. (Folder 55: 3)
    Includes memoranda and printed matter
  - Statements by members of the committee, 1930. (Folder 55: 4)
  - Letters relating to the appointment of committee members, 1929-1930. (Folder 55: 5)
    Includes list of suggested members, memoranda, and telegram
  - Minutes of meetings, 1929-1930. (Folder 55: 6-9)
    New York City, 1929 November 11; Chicago, 1930 March 8; Boston, 1930 June 10; and Washington, D.C., 1930 November 19
  - Lists of chairmen, research secretaries, and members, 1930 and undated. (Folder 55: 10)
    Includes correspondence, list of assignments, and organizational chart
  - Subcommittees
    - Home Care
      - Correspondence and organization plan, 1930 and undated (Folder 55: 11)
      - Minutes of meeting, 1930 (Folder 55: 12)
    - Committee of Frances Taussig (Subcommittee of Home Care), 1930. (Folder 55: 13)
      Clipping, correspondence, memoranda, outline, press release, and statement
    - Mothers' Aid, 1930-1931
      - Article, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, statement of philosophy, and study, 1930-1931 (Folder 55: 14)
      - Article and letter relating to housekeeping service to help children from motherless family, 1930 (Folder 55: 15)
  - "Study on Day Nurseries: Activities and Social Policies," Mary F. Bogue and Katherine F. Blake, undated (Box-folder 56: 1)
  - Central office records
    - Proceedings of sessions, New York City, 1929 November 11 (Folder 56: 2)
    - Miscellany, 1930-1931. (Folder 56: 3)
      Includes correspondence, lists of members and chairmen, and outline
  - Editorial correspondence, 1931-1932 (Folder 56: 4)
  - Expenses records, 1929-1931. (Folder 56: 5)
  - Martha Van Rensselaer--Correspondence, 1930. (Folder 56: 6)
    Includes a summary of the White House Conference on Dependent Children, 1909
  - Letters of acceptance from individuals to serve on the committee, 1929-1930 (Folder 56: 7)
  - H. E. Bernard, 1929-1931. (Folder 56: 8)
    Article, clipping, correspondence, printed matter, statement, and telegram